[
  [
    {
      "question": "Rajender is working as a delivery boy in a multinational company. The company is paying him ₹90 per delivery. In a fortnight comprising 15 consecutive working days, his average earnings per day was ₹540. If his average earnings of the first 7 days was ₹519 per day and that of the last 7 days was ₹546 per day, then at was his earning on the 8th day of the fortnight?",
      "options": ["₹571", "₹681", "₹661", "₹645"],
      "answer": "₹645",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average weight of a group of 12 children is 66 kg. If 2 children, X and Y, replace A and B, the new average weight becomes 65 kg. The weight of A= weight of B and the weight of X = weight of Y. Another child, C, is included in the group, and the new average weight remains 65 kg. Weight of C= weight of X. Find the weight of A.",
      "options": ["69 kg", "72 kg", "71 kg", "67 kg"],
      "answer": "71 kg",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sudesh is the owner of a multipurpose shop. For a specific month, his profits are detailed below. Category Profit earned in ₹ Groceries 50,000 Cosmetics 20,000 Ladies' dresses 10,000 In order to estimate the expected profit for the next month, he assigns the weights of 6, 5 and 8 to the different categories in the same order. What will be the weighted average of his profits?",
      "options": ["₹25,265.18 (nearly)","₹24,863.16 (nearly)","₹25,163.16 (nearly)","₹25,263.16 (nearly)"],
      "answer": "₹25,263.16 (nearly)",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a school excursion each student of junior school was charged ₹325 and each student of senior school was charged ₹400. If there were 80 students from junior school and the combined average amount charged per student was ₹352, then how many students from senior school went for the excursion?",
      "options": ["55", "45", "50", "40"],
      "answer": "45",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "In ₹150, B buys 10 pens for ₹8 each, 10 erasers for ₹5 each and some sharpeners for ₹4 each. What is the average price per item in ₹?",
      "options": ["8", "7", "10", "6"],
      "answer": "6",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "20 students of a college went to a hotel. 19 of them spent ₹175 each on their meal and the 20th student spent ₹19 more than the average of all the 20. Find the total money spent by them.",
      "options": ["₹3,490", "₹3,540", "₹3,520", "₹3,500"],
      "answer": "₹3,520",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average score in a test for 50 students is 44. Out of the total students, 40% of the students are girls and the rest are boys. The average score of boys is 20% less than that of girls. What is the average score of girls?",
      "options": ["50", "54", "48", "52"],
      "answer": "50",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "A is the average of 10 given numbers. B is the average after 2 of the numbers were replaced by 3 other different numbers. The average of the removed numbers is 48 and the average of the newly included numbers is 56. If A + B = 438, then the value of A - B is:",
      "options": ["21", "14", "12", "26"],
      "answer": "14",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "Average of 8 numbers is 44. The average of first three numbers is 50 and the average of next two numbers is 52. If the sixth number is 6 and 8 less than seventh and eighth number respectively, then what is the value of eighth number?",
      "options": ["36", "32", "40", "56"],
      "answer": "36",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "Eleven friends spent Rs. 18 each on a tour and the twelfth friend spent Rs. 11 less than the average expenditure of all twelve of them. What is the total money spent by twelve friends",
      "options": ["Rs.204", "Rs.215", "Rs.212", "Rs.208"],
      "answer": "Rs.204",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sonali applied for a job of Science teacher in a school. In the test for job, she scored 8 in physics, 8 in chemistry, 6 in biology, and 6.5 in the interview. For calculating the final score, weightage of 2, 3, 3, and 4 were assigned to Physics, Chemistry, Biology and interview, respectively. What is the weighted average score of Sonali ?",
      "options": ["7", "8.4", "7.2", "21"],
      "answer": "7",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The batting average for 27 innings of a cricket player is 47 runs. His highest score in an innings exceeds his lowest score by 157 runs. If these two innings are excluded, the average score of the remaining 25 innings is 42 runs. Find his highest score in an innings.",
      "options": ["176", "188", "186", "174"],
      "answer": "188",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an office, 80% workers are men while 20% are women. The average age of the men is 30 and the average age of the women is 40. What is the average age of all the workers in that office?",
      "options": ["50", "32", "30", "35"],
      "answer": "32",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average age of a husband and his wife 3 years ago was 39 years. The average age of the husband, wife and their child 2 years hence will be 34 years. Find the present age of the child.",
      "options": ["12 years", "16 years", "15 years", "18 years"],
      "answer": "12 years",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a family of six males and a few females, the average monthly consumption of grain head is 14.4 kg. If the average monthly consumption per head is 20 kg in the case of males and 6 kg in the case of females. Find the number of females in the family?",
      "options": ["8", "4", "6", "7"],
      "answer": "4",
      "category": "Average"
    }
  ],
  [
    {
      "question": "A is the average marks of a group of 10 students in a class and A+8 is the average of a group of 15 students which includes the group of 10 students as given. The total marks obtained by the group of 10 students is X and the total marks obtained by the group of 15 students is Y. If X : Y = 3 : 5, then the value of A + X + Y is _________.",
      "options": ["1964", "1845", "2012", "1992"],
      "answer": "1992",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "A retailer opens her outlet on all seven days of the week. It is observed that her average sales for Saturdays and Sundays combined is ₹ 300, and ₹ 200 for the remaining five days combined. For a month starting on saturday, it was found that the total sales were ₹7,000. Which among the following months it could be",
      "options": ["March", "April", "Jan", "Feb"],
      "answer": "April",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider ten consecutive odd numbers starting from 5. Multiply each of them, except the first and the second, with three. What will be the average of the ten numbers so formed?",
      "options": ["39.6", "39", "42", "38.4"],
      "answer": "39.6",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the average of numbers from 1 to 50 which are multiples of 2 or 5? (correct to one decimal place)",
      "options": ["25.4", "25.9", "26.4", "25.8"],
      "answer": "25.8",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average weight of students of section A and B having 40 students each is 45.5 kg and 44.2 kg respectively. Two students of section A having average weight 48.75 kg were shifted to B and 2 students of section B were shifted to section A, making the average weight of both the sections equal. What is the average weight (in kg) of the students who were shifted from section B to section A?",
      "options": ["34.5", "35", "35.75", "34.25"],
      "answer": "35.75",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an examination, the average score of a student was 67.6. If he would have got 27 more marks in Mathematics, 10 more marks in Computer Science, 18 more marks in History and retained the same marks in other subjects, then his average score would have been 72.6. How many papers were there in the examination?",
      "options": ["11", "10", "12", "9"],
      "answer": "11",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average monthly salary of 60 employees of a factory is Rs.29900. If two officers are getting Rs.90,000 each and the average salary of 8 supervisors is Rs.65,000, then what is the average salary (in Rs.) of the remaining employees?",
      "options": ["21080", "22680", "29080", "21880"],
      "answer": "21880",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the ratio of the average of first eight prime numbers to the average of first ten even natural numbers?",
      "options": ["1 : 7", "7 : 80", "8 : 70", "7 : 8"],
      "answer": "7 : 8",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "x, y and z are three positive numbers such that y is 4/5 times of x and z is 5/8 times of y. If the average of reciprocals of the numbers x, y and z is 17/240, then the average of 3 times of x and 5 times of y will be:",
      "options": ["70", "60", "40", "45"],
      "answer": "70",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The numbers 2, 3, 4 and 5 occur (2 + 5k), (5k - 7), (2k - 3) and (k + 2) times, respectively. The average of the number is 2.85. Later on, the number 2 was replaced by 6 in all the places. What is the average of the new numbers?",
      "options": ["2.4", "5.25", "3.85", "4.75"],
      "answer": "5.25",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "If the average of the 3-digit numbers 335, 2x5, x35, 63x and 406 is 411, then what will be the average of (x - 1), (x - 3), (x + 3) and (x + 5) ?",
      "options": ["6", "3", "5", "4"],
      "answer": "5",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average of the numbers a, b, c and d is 2d + 4, Also, the averages of the numbers a and b, b and c, c and d are 8, 5 and 4, respectively. If e = a + d + 1, then what is the average of the numbers d and e ?",
      "options": ["8", "8.5", "3", "7"],
      "answer": "8",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average of four consecutive odd natural numbers is eight less than the average of three consecutive even natural numbers. If the sum of these even numbers is equal to the sum of above four odd numbers, then the average of four original odd numbers is:",
      "options": ["36", "24", "18", "32"],
      "answer": "24",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The average of nine 2 digit numbers is decreased by 6 when the digits of one of the 2 digit numbers is interchanged. Find the difference between the digits of that number.",
      "options": ["6", "4", "2", "8"],
      "answer": "6",
      "category": "Average"
    },
    {
      "question": "The numbers 24, 45, a, 35, 59, 83, 46, b, 29, 74 are serially numbered as they appear in the sequence. When each number is added to its serial number, then the average of the new numbers formed is 55. The average of the missing numbers (a and b) is:",
      "options": ["38", "58", "62", "50"],
      "answer": "50",
      "category": "Average"
    }
  ],
  [
	{
		 "question" : "The average of 35 consecutive natural numbers is N. Dropping the first 10 numbers and including the next 10 numbers, the average is changed to M. If the value of M^2 - N^2 = 600, then the average of 3M and 5N is:",
		 "options" : ["90","120","100","115"],
		 "answer" : "115",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "A batsman in his 11th innings makes a score of 77 runs, thereby increasing his average scores by 3. What is his average score after the 11th innings?",
		 "options" : ["46","49","47","48"],
		 "answer" : "47",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average age of husband, wife and child 7 years ago was 42 years and that of wife and child 9 years ago was 36 years. The present age of the husband is:",
		 "options" : ["50","55","48","57"],
		 "answer" : "57",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "A batsman scores 92 runs in the 15th innings and thus increases his average by 4. What is his average after the 15th innings?",
		 "options" : ["40","32","35","36"],
		 "answer" : "36",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average age of 120 students in a group is 13.56 years, 35% of the number of students are girls and the rest are boys. If the ratio of the average age of boys and girls is 6:5, then what is the average age (in years) of the girls?",
		 "options" : ["12","11.6","10","14.4"],
		 "answer" : "12",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of 18 numbers is 37.5. If six numbers of average x are added to them, then the average of all the numbers increases by one. The value of x is",
		 "options" : ["40","41.5","42","38.5"],
		 "answer" : "41.5",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average weight of a certain number of students in a group is 72 kg. If 10 students having an average weight of 78 kg leave and 4 students having an average weight of 80 kg join the group, the average weight of the students in the group decreases by 0.7 kg. The number of students initially in the group is :",
		 "options" : ["56","46","44","54"],
		 "answer" : "46",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of 33 numbers is 74. The average of the first 17 numbers is 72.8 and that of the last 17 numbers is 77.2. If the 17th number is excluded, then what will be the average of the remaining numbers (correct to one decimal place)?",
		 "options" : ["72.9","73.4","71.6","70.8"],
		 "answer" : "72.9",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The number of students in a class is 75, out of which 33 1/3% are boys and the rest are girls. The average score in mathematics of the boys is 66 2/3% more than that of the girls. If the average score of all the students is 66, then the average score of the girls is:",
		 "options" : ["52","55","54","58"],
		 "answer" : "54",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The owner of a bike buys petrol at the rate of Rs. 64, Rs. 80 and Rs. 320 per litre for three consecutive years. If he spends Rs. 32000 on petrol every year, then what is the average price (Rs.) of petrol per litre ?",
		 "options" : ["120","84","108","96"],
		 "answer" : "96",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "An art exhibition was held in the month of november. The numbers of visitors on weekdays and on weekends were 450 and 750 respectively. If the first day of the month was Monday, then what was the average number of visitors in the month ?",
		 "options" : ["520","530","510","540"],
		 "answer" : "530",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "A person was asked to guess his own weight. He estimated his weight to be over 70 kg but less than 80 kg. His friend estimated his weight to be more than 74 kg but less than 84 kg. His mother said that his weight is less than 78 kg. Assuming that the weights are a whole number and that the three had correctly guessed, then what is the average of the possible weights(in Kg)?",
		 "options" : ["76.5","76","77","75"],
		 "answer" : "76",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "A party was held for 50 people on their own expenses. Out of them, 48 people paid Rs. 950 each and the other two persons paid Rs. 1200 more than the average expenses of the group. The total amount spent was :",
		 "options" : ["Rs 75,000","Rs 40,000","Rs 25,000","Rs 50,000"],
		 "answer" : "Rs 50,000",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "Out of four numbers the average of the first three is 16 and that of the last three is 15. If the last number is 21 then the first number is:",
		 "options" : ["28","22","21","24"],
		 "answer" : "24",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of all the prime and composite numbers upto 100 is:",
		 "options" : ["51","50","50.5","49.5"],
		 "answer" : "51",
		 "category" : "Average"
	}
],
[
	{
		 "question" : "What is the average of the first 15 whole numbers?",
		 "options" : ["8","7","9","10"],
		 "answer" : "7",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "What is the average of the first 8 multiples of 6 among the natural numbers?",
		 "options" : ["24","26","27","28"],
		 "answer" : "27",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of a and b is 36. The average of b and c is 42. What is the difference between c and a ?",
		 "options" : ["18","12","16","14"],
		 "answer" : "12",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of 1088 real numbers is zero. At most how many of them can be negative?",
		 "options" : ["100","88","544","1087"],
		 "answer" : "1087",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The difference between the average of first ten prime numbers and the first ten prime numbers of two digits is:",
		 "options" : ["14.5","16.5","12.5","13.5"],
		 "answer" : "13.5",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of the first 101 ______ numbers is equal to 102.",
		 "options" : ["natural","odd","even","perfect square"],
		 "answer" : "even",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of the first 1234 _______ numbers is equal to 1234.",
		 "options" : ["odd","even","prime","natural"],
		 "answer" : "odd",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of a number and its reciprocal is 4. The average of its cube and cube of its reciprocal is equal to:",
		 "options" : ["256","142","288","244"],
		 "answer" : "244",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average age of four brothers is 15 years. If their father is included, the average is increased by 5 years. The age of the father (in years) is:",
		 "options" : ["35","40","38","36"],
		 "answer" : "40",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "10 years ago, the average age of a family of five members was 38 years. Now, two new members join, whose age difference is 8 years. If the present average age of the family is the same as it was 10 years ago, what is the age (in years) of the new younger member?",
		 "options" : ["15","9","10","17"],
		 "answer" : "9",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of n number is 36. If each of 75% of the numbers is increased by 6 and each of the remaining numbers is decreased by 9, then the new average of the numbers is:",
		 "options" : ["37.125","33.75","38.25","36.25"],
		 "answer" : "38.25",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average weight of the students in a group was 75.4 kg. Later on, four students having weights, 72.9 kg, 73.8 kg, 79.5 kg and 87.4 kg joined the group. As a result, the average weight of all the students in the group increased by 0.24 kg. What was the number of students in the group, initially ?",
		 "options" : ["46","36","50","48"],
		 "answer" : "46",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "In a class of 80 students, 60% participate in games and the rest do not. The average weight of the former group is 5% more than that of the latter. If the average weight of all the students is 51 1/2 kg, then what is the average weight (in kg) of the former group?",
		 "options" : ["57.6","54.5","60","52.5"],
		 "answer" : "52.5",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "The average of 27 numbers is zero. Out of them, how many may be greater than zero, at the most?",
		 "options" : ["0","15","26","20"],
		 "answer" : "26",
		 "category" : "Average"
	},
	{
		 "question" : "In a class of 40 students, 45% are girls and the remaining are boys. If the average marks of the girls is 54 and that of the boys is 46, what is the average of the whole class?",
		 "options" : ["49.8","49.7","49.6","49.5"],
		 "answer" : "49.6",
		 "category" : "Average"
	}
],
	[
		{
			 "question" : "The average marks of 40 students was found to be 68. If the marks of two students were incorrectly entered as 48 and 64 instead of 84 and 46 respectively, then what is the correct average?",
			 "options" : ["68.25","68.15","68.45","68.35"],
			 "answer" : "68.45",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Four different positive numbers are written in ascending order. One-third of the average of all the four numbers is 19 less than the greatest of these numbers. If the average of the first three numbers is 12, the greatest number among the given numbers is:",
			 "options" : ["25","22","24","21"],
			 "answer" : "24",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The total number of students in section A and B of a class is 110. The number of students in section A is 10 more than that of section B. The average score of the students in B, in a test, is 20% more than that of students in A. If the average score of all the students in the class is 72, then what is the average score of the students in A?",
			 "options" : ["66","68","63","70"],
			 "answer" : "66",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Three numbers are such that if the average of any two of them is added to the third number, the sums obtained are 168, 174 and 180 respectively. What is the average of the original three numbers?",
			 "options" : ["86","87","89","84"],
			 "answer" : "87",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of a certain number of students in a class is 68.5 kg. If 4 new students having weights 72.2 kg, 70.8kg, 70.3kg and 66.7 kg join the class, then the average weight of all the students increases by 300 g. The number of students in the class, initially is:",
			 "options" : ["21","16","11","26"],
			 "answer" : "16",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of twelve numbers is 42. The average of the last five numbers is 40 and that of the first four numbers is 44. The 6th number is 6 less than the fifth and 5 less than the 7th number. The average of the 5th and the 7th numbers is:",
			 "options" : ["44","44.5","43","43.5"],
			 "answer" : "44.5",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "At a Yoga center, 60% of the members are men and 40% of the members are women. If the average age of the men is 55 years and the average age of the women is 45 years, then what is the average age (in years) of all the members ?",
			 "options" : ["51","48","50","49"],
			 "answer" : "51",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of 40 students of a school is 52 kg. If the weight of the teacher is included, the average weight rises by 500 grams. Find the weight (in kg) of the teacher.",
			 "options" : ["72.5","74.5","73.5","71.5"],
			 "answer" : "72.5",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average salary of all 40 employees, including 35 non-teaching staff members, of a school is ₹4,000. If the average salary of the non-teaching staff members is ₹4,200, find the average salary of the remaining staff of the school.",
			 "options" : ["₹3,600","₹2,600","₹2,800","₹2,300"],
			 "answer" : "₹2,600",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of the first eight multiples of 6 is:",
			 "options" : ["24","27","30","25"],
			 "answer" : "27",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Find the average of the prime numbers lying between 69 and 92.",
			 "options" : ["79","82","80","81"],
			 "answer" : "79",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of the first thirteen persons among fourteen persons is 78 kg. The weight of the 14th person is 39 kg more than the average weight of all the fourteen persons. Find the weight of the 14th person.",
			 "options" : ["118 kg","98 kg","110 kg","120 kg"],
			 "answer" : "120 kg",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of 15 people increases by 3.2 kg when a new person comes in place of one of them weighing 52 kg. The weight of the new person is:",
			 "options" : ["96 kg","100 kg","52 kg","48 kg"],
			 "answer" : "100 kg",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of A, B and C is 77 kg. If the average weight of A and B is 68 kg and that of B and C is 83 kg, then the weight (in kg) of B is:",
			 "options" : ["71","74","67","73"],
			 "answer" : "71",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of 45 numbers was found to be 39. Later on, it was detected that a number 65 was misread as 56. Find the correct average of the given numbers.",
			 "options" : ["36.2","37.2","38.2","39.2"],
			 "answer" : "39.2",
			 "category" : "Average"
		}
	],
	[
		{
			 "question" : "What is the average of the first six prime numbers?",
			 "options" : ["6 2/3","6 5/6","6 1/6","6 1/3"],
			 "answer" : "6 5/6",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Rakesh runs a coaching institute having 50 faculty members. The average monthly salary of 35 faculty members is ₹37,500. What will be the average monthly salary (in ₹) of the other 15 faculty members, if the average monthly salary of all the 50 faculty members is found to be ₹30,000?",
			 "options" : ["12,000","13,000","12,500","13,500"],
			 "answer" : "12,500",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "In a class of 37 students, there are 22 girls. The average weight of these girls is 46 kg and the average weight of the whole class is 50 kg. What is the average weight (in kg) of the boys in that class ? (Rounded off to 2 decimal places)",
			 "options" : ["60.74","55.87","61.35","58.25"],
			 "answer" : "55.87",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Student gets 62, 58, 72, 58 and 83 marks in Sanskrit, English, Mathematics, Social and Computer Science, respectively. His average marks in Mathematics, Social and Computer Science are ______ more than the average marks in Sanskrit, English and Mathematics.",
			 "options" : ["9","8","6","7"],
			 "answer" : "7",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average marks of 13 students in a subject is 66. If the average of the first seven students is 67 and that of the last seven students is 69, then the marks of the seventh student is:",
			 "options" : ["99","91","97","94"],
			 "answer" : "94",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of the first 10 prime number is:",
			 "options" : ["12.9","9.7","11.9","13.4"],
			 "answer" : "12.9",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of the first 69 natural numbers is:",
			 "options" : ["34","35","33","36"],
			 "answer" : "35",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "What is the average of the first 13 multiples of 3 ?",
			 "options" : ["21","39","42","35"],
			 "answer" : "21",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average age of a family of three members (mother, father and Son) is 44 years. After the son's marriage, the average age of the family becomes 39 years. What is the age of the daughter-in-law ?",
			 "options" : ["24 years","25 years","23 years","22 years"],
			 "answer" : "24 years",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of 20 students of a class was 30.5 kg. After 6 new students joined the class, its average weight increased by 2 kg. Find the average weight of the 6 new students who joined the class (rounded off to one decimal place).",
			 "options" : ["30.5 kg","32.5 kg","39.2 kg","38.5 kg"],
			 "answer" : "39.2 kg",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "A batsman makes 96 runs in the 13th innings and thus his average increases by 3. Find his average after 13 innings.",
			 "options" : ["65","50","70","60"],
			 "answer" : "60",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of four consecutive odd numbers is 58. What is the lowest number ?",
			 "options" : ["51","57","55","53"],
			 "answer" : "55",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "In April, Mr. Khan observed that his balance in his bank account is ₹5,600 for the first 24 days, ₹12,000 for the next two days and ₹37,500 in the last 4 days of the month. What is his daily average balance for April ?",
			 "options" : ["₹10,280","₹15,280","₹10,480","₹14,280"],
			 "answer" : "₹10,280",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "There are 48 students in a class. Their average weight is 48 kg. When one student leaves the class, the average weight reduces by 200 grams. What is the weight of the student who left the class?",
			 "options" : ["57.4 kg","54.7 kg","45.7 kg","47.5 kg"],
			 "answer" : "57.4 kg",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of A, B and C is 43 kg. If the average weight of A and B is 40 kg and that of B and C is 41 kg, then the weight (in kg) of B is ?",
			 "options" : ["41","43","33","37"],
			 "answer" : "33",
			 "category" : "Average"
		}
	],
	[
		{
			 "question" : "The speed of a bus from station A to B is 55 km/h, and while coming back from station B to A, the speed of the bus is 95 km/h. The average speed (in km/h) of the bus during the whole journey is :",
			 "options" : ["72 1/3","67 1/3","62 2/3","69 2/3"],
			 "answer" : "69 2/3",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "A student's marks were incorrectly entered as 44 instead of 86. Due to this, the average of the class got decreased by 3/2. What is the number of students in the class ?",
			 "options" : ["24","28","36","30"],
			 "answer" : "28",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of some students in class 12th was 56 kg. When seven students whose average weight was 58 kg joined the class, the average weight of all the students increased by 200 gm. Find the number of students in the class in the beginning?",
			 "options" : ["56","77","49","63"],
			 "answer" : "63",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "There are 75 students in the hostel. Due to new admissions, 15 new students join the mess, and the daily expenses of the mess increased by ₹240, while the average expenditure per head diminished by ₹5. What was the original expenditure (in ₹) of the mess?",
			 "options" : ["3,450","4,530","3,540","4,350"],
			 "answer" : "3,450",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average age of the boys in the class was 16 years. When 4 boys whose average age was 13 years are admitted to the class, the average age of the class was reduced by 6 months. How many boys were there initially in the class ?",
			 "options" : ["22","20","18","25"],
			 "answer" : "20",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "In a school, the average height of the students of the tenth standard is 100 cm. The average height of boys is 118 cm, whereas the average height of girls is 95 cm. What is the number of girls in the class if there are 20 boys?",
			 "options" : ["72","63","54","36"],
			 "answer" : "72",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Sandeep drives a distance of 500 metres to a store in 175 seconds. Then he drives 400 metres to another store in 125 seconds. What is his average speed (in m/s)?",
			 "options" : ["3.5","3","2","2.5"],
			 "answer" : "3",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "In a subject, there are 40 marks for practical and 110 marks for theory. In another subject, the practical marks are 60 and the theory marks are 40. If R gets an average mark of 40 in practical and an average mark of 60 in theory, then his average marks per subject are ______ .",
			 "options" : ["80","60","100","40"],
			 "answer" : "100",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "While calculating the average marks of a class, the score increased by 0.5 when the marks of one student is wrongly entered as 54 instead of 45. The number of students in the class is:",
			 "options" : ["36","18","45","54"],
			 "answer" : "18",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "If the average marks of three sections of Class IX, having 25, 35 and 40 students, respectively is 60, 70 and 80, then the average marks of all the students of Class IX is:",
			 "options" : ["75","71.5","70.5","72"],
			 "answer" : "71.5",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "What is the average of natural numbers from 1 to 73 ?",
			 "options" : ["28","37","30","34"],
			 "answer" : "37",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "S gets 65, 74, 62, 68 and 68 marks in Hindi, English, Mathematics, Physics and Chemistry, respectively. His average marks in Mathematics, Hindi and English are _______ more than the average marks in Mathematics, Physics and Chemistry.",
			 "options" : ["0.5","1.33","1.67","1"],
			 "answer" : "1",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of group A and group B is 12 kg and 24 kg, respectively. The ratio of the members in group A to group B is 1 : 2. Find the combined average of both the groups.",
			 "options" : ["16 kg","22 kg","20 kg","18 kg"],
			 "answer" : "20 kg",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of the group of 12 players increases by 1.5 kg when a player who weighs 63 kg is replaced by a new player. What is the weight of the new player?",
			 "options" : ["84 kg","81 kg","83 kg","79 kg"],
			 "answer" : "81 kg",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Find the average of the prime numbers lying between 51 and 77.",
			 "options" : ["65","64","67","66"],
			 "answer" : "64",
			 "category" : "Average"
		}
	],
	[
		{
			 "question" : "The average monthly salary of workers in a factory is ₹6,000. The average monthly salary of 100 technicians is ₹12,000, and the average monthly salary of non-technicians is ₹4,000. Find the total number of workers in the factory.",
			 "options" : ["400","300","250","450"],
			 "answer" : "400",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average age of 30 students in a class is 12 years. The average age of a group of 5 of the students is 10 years and that of another group of 5 of them is 14 years. The average of the remaining students is:",
			 "options" : ["14 years","12 years","11 years","13 years"],
			 "answer" : "12 years",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average age of 25 students in a class is 14 years. Five new students with an average age of 14.6 years join this class. What is the average age of 30 students in the class ?",
			 "options" : ["13.1 years","14.1 years","15.1 years","16.1 years"],
			 "answer" : "14.1 years",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average number of runs scored by a cricketer in 42 innings is 30. The difference between his maximum and minimum scores in an inning is 100. If these two innings are not taken into consideration, then the average score of the remaining 40 innings is 28. What are the maximum runs scored by him in an inning?",
			 "options" : ["120","105","115","110"],
			 "answer" : "120",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of 18 integers is found to be 41. It was detected that by mistake the integer 127 was copied as 341, while calculating the average. Then the correct average is:",
			 "options" : ["23 1/7","33 1/9","29 1/9","37 1/3"],
			 "answer" : "29 1/9",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "A man bought 13 chairs at ₹150 each and 15 chairs at ₹130 each. The average price of a chair (to the nearest rupee) is:",
			 "options" : ["₹130","₹145","₹142","₹139"],
			 "answer" : "₹139",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of 36 numbers was found to be 45. Later, it was detected that 84 was misread as 48. Find the correct average of the given numbers.",
			 "options" : ["58","48","46","56"],
			 "answer" : "46",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "According to Raghav, his weight is more than 64 kg but less than 74 kg. His sister does not agree with Raghv and she thinks that his weight is more than 60 kg but less than 69 kg. His mother’s view is that his weight cannot be more than 68 kg. His father’s view is that his weight cannot be more than 67 kg. If all are them are correct in their estimation, then what is the average of different probable weights of Raghav measures (in kg)?",
			 "options" : ["66","67","68","65"],
			 "answer" : "66",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average monthly income of the father and mother is ₹5,000. The average monthly income of the mother and her son is ₹6,000. The average monthly income of the father and his son is ₹10,000. Find the monthly income (in ₹) of the father.",
			 "options" : ["9000","8000","12000","10000"],
			 "answer" : "9000",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "College P has 180 students scoring average marks of 88 and college Q has 320 students scoring average marks of 72. Find the average marks of both the colleges together.",
			 "options" : ["82.00","75.25","77.76","80.00"],
			 "answer" : "77.76",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "In an examination of 7 papers of 100 marks each, there were 3 mathematics papers, 2 English papers and 2 Hindi papers. D gets average marks of 45, 55 and 60 in mathematics, English and Hindi, respectively. What are the average marks per paper?",
			 "options" : ["56.5","52.1","55.6","54.1"],
			 "answer" : "52.1",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of all prime numbers between 32 and 69 is:",
			 "options" : ["52.5","60","51","56.5"],
			 "answer" : "51",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average weight of 30 students in a class is 60 kg. If the weight of the class teacher is included, the average increases by 0.5 kg. The weight (in kg) of the teacher is:",
			 "options" : ["76.5","75.5","72.5","74.5"],
			 "answer" : "75.5",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average marks of 13 students is 67. If the average marks of the first seven students is 61 and that of the last seven students is 65, then what is the marks of the 7 students now? 𝑡ℎ",
			 "options" : ["11","9","7","6"],
			 "answer" : "11",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "In a company, the total customer calls on Monday, Wednesday and Friday are 15,500 and the total calls on Tuesday and Thursday are 12,500. The average calls on Saturday and Sunday are 7,000. What are the average calls per day in a week?",
			 "options" : ["6500","7500","7000","6000"],
			 "answer" : "6000",
			 "category" : "Average"
		}
	],
	[
		{
			 "question" : "A class of 40 students took a mathematics test. 18 students had an average score of 75. The other students had an average score of 62. What is the average score of the entire class?",
			 "options" : ["67.85","72.52","68.50","69.85"],
			 "answer" : "67.85",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "What is the average marks of all the students if the average marks of three batches of 55, 60, and 45 students is 50, 55, and 60, respectively ?",
			 "options" : ["51.23","55.98","57.42","54.68"],
			 "answer" : "54.68",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of the square of first five even natural numbers is:",
			 "options" : ["40","44","42","46"],
			 "answer" : "44",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of 10 numbers is 42. If each number is increased by 5, then what will be the new average ?",
			 "options" : ["42","47","92","57"],
			 "answer" : "47",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Average marks obtained by 19 boys of a college is 48. If the highest marks and lowest marks obtained are removed, then the average reduces by 4. What is the average of the highest and lowest marks obtained ?",
			 "options" : ["76","80","84","82"],
			 "answer" : "82",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of 24 numbers is 43. If we subtract a number 'M' from each number, then the average becomes 38. What was the value of M?",
			 "options" : ["12","5","7","10"],
			 "answer" : "5",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of five consecutive numbers is 53. What is the biggest of these numbers?",
			 "options" : ["52","55","53","54"],
			 "answer" : "55",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average age of 15 members of a committee is increased by 4 years when two members whose ages are 60 years and 70 years are replaced by the two new members. What is the average age of the new members?",
			 "options" : ["105 years","80 years","85 years","95 years"],
			 "answer" : "95 years",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of five consecutive odd numbers is 15. What is the smallest of these five numbers ?",
			 "options" : ["11","13","15","9"],
			 "answer" : "11",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Average price of 20 pens is Rs. 18. If 12 new pens are added, then the average price rise by Rs. 4. What is the total price of the new pens?",
			 "options" : ["Rs.384","Rs.368","Rs.328","Rs.344"],
			 "answer" : "Rs.344",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average expenditure of Raman for 5 days is Rs. 160. If his expenditure for the first 4 days is Rs. 90, Rs. 135, Rs. 75 and Rs. 180 respectively, then what is his expenditure on the 5th day ?",
			 "options" : ["Rs.360","Rs.320","Rs.280","Rs.250"],
			 "answer" : "Rs.320",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Average of 4 numbers is 45. Average of first two numbers is thrice the Average of other two numbers. What is the sum of first two numbers?",
			 "options" : ["122","105","125","135"],
			 "answer" : "135",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average height of 40 sticks is 156 cm. Some sticks of average height 162 cm are taken out. If the new average height is 150 cm, then how many sticks are remaining?",
			 "options" : ["25","20","16","32"],
			 "answer" : "20",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Among four students sitting in a row, average age of last three students is 48 years and the average age of first three students is 50 years. If the age of first student is 56 years, then what is the age of the last student?",
			 "options" : ["30","40","50","60"],
			 "answer" : "50",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Average of 11 numbers is 8. If every number is tripled, then what will be the new average of the numbers?",
			 "options" : ["8","24","16","32"],
			 "answer" : "24",
			 "category" : "Average"
		}
	],
	[
		{
			 "question" : "What will be the average of all the even numbers between 5 and 29?",
			 "options" : ["14","19","22","17"],
			 "answer" : "17",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Average of 24 observations is 41. Average of first 9 observations is 42. Average of last 16 observations is 39. What is the value of 9th observation ?",
			 "options" : ["14","24","18","20"],
			 "answer" : "18",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "A group of students has an average weight of 42 kg. One student of weight 48 kg leaves the group and another student of weight 44 kg joins the group. If the new average weight becomes 41.6 kg, then how many students are there in the group?",
			 "options" : ["15","10","8","12"],
			 "answer" : "10",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of 7 consecutive odd numbers is A. If next 3 and previous 2 odd numbers to these 7 odd numbers are also included, then what is the new average of these 12 consecutive odd numbers?",
			 "options" : ["A + 1","A - 2","A + 2","A + 3"],
			 "answer" : "A + 1",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of marks obtained by S1 and S2 is 30 more than the average marks obtained by S2 and S3. If the marks obtained by S3 is 50, then what are the marks obtained by S1?",
			 "options" : ["80","105","95","110"],
			 "answer" : "110",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "What is the average of the squares of the first 13 natural numbers?",
			 "options" : ["63","74","65","72"],
			 "answer" : "63",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Seven friends each spent Rs. 16 and the eighth friend spent Rs.35 more than the average of all the eight. What is the total amount spent by them?",
			 "options" : ["Rs. 148","Rs. 176","Rs. 168","Rs. 160"],
			 "answer" : "Rs. 168",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average age of 120 members of a society is 62.5 years. By addition of 30 new members, the average age becomes 58.2 years. What is the average age of newly joined members?",
			 "options" : ["40 years","41 years","39 years","42 years"],
			 "answer" : "41 years",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average age of a class of 6 girls is x years. Four new girls having ages x- 2, x + 4, x + 8 and x + 10 joins the class. What is the new average age of the class?",
			 "options" : ["x - 2","x + 2","x + 5","x + 1"],
			 "answer" : "x + 2",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Average of 9 consecutive odd numbers is 27. If the previous and next odd number to these 9 odd numbers are also included, then what will be the new average?",
			 "options" : ["32","28","29","27"],
			 "answer" : "27",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "In a school average weight of girls and boys are 30 kg and 36 kg. If the number of girls is twice of the number of boys, then what will be the average weight of all the students in school?",
			 "options" : ["31 kg","31.5 kg","32 kg","33 kg"],
			 "answer" : "32 kg",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "The average of 10 consecutive integers is 33/2 What is the average of first three integers?",
			 "options" : ["12","13","15","11"],
			 "answer" : "13",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "2 years ago the average age of husband, wife and child was 28 years, and 5 years ago the average age of husband and child was 21 years. What is the present age of the wife?",
			 "options" : ["38 years","40 years","36 years","42 years"],
			 "answer" : "38 years",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "Average of the marks of 132 students of a college is 50. If the average of the marks of the passed students is 55 and the average of the marks of the failed students is 35, then what will be the respective ratio of the total marks of passed students and the total marks of failed students?",
			 "options" : ["1 : 3","11 : 7","33 : 7","21 : 8"],
			 "answer" : "33 : 7",
			 "category" : "Average"
		},
		{
			 "question" : "10 Consecutive numbers are given. If the average of the two numbers given in the middle is 13.5, then what is the sum of the first 6 numbers?",
			 "options" : ["58","55","67","69"],
			 "answer" : "69",
			 "category" : "Average"
		}
	]
]